## **Emmanuel Milou**

Software Engineer, Technical Lead 5139 rue de Brébeuf, H2J 3L8, Montreal, Québec CA

manumilou in manumilou

I have 10+ years experience as a Free software consultant, developer and technical lead. My technical background goes from embedded and C development to web applications, content management systems, APIs development and CI/CD pipelines implementation. I was team manager and technical lead in our web development department (up to 25 developers) for several years. I am looking to have a positive impact in a position that will provide both inspiring human interactions and interesting technical challenges.

#### **SKILLS**

## Languages

php | python | bash | mysql |
javascript | c++ | c

#### Misc

git | jenkins | gitlab ci | sonarqube | rest api | testing | tdd | ci/cd | redis

#### **Transversal**

communication | empathy | team | leadership | solution-oriented | agile

## Frameworks / CMS

laravel | django | drupal | wagtail | wordpress

#### **Containers**

docker | lxc | lxd | openshift | kubernetes

### Learning

ruby | rails | haskell | ansible | chef

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

**Technical Director, Web Solutions** at Savoir-faire Linux, Montreal **November 2016- August 2017** 

http://savoirfairelinux.com

project management | architecture | team | devops | ci/cd | agile

- Streamlined testing and delivery processes among the different stack teams
- Helped on and reviewed projects estimates produced by the developers
- Engaged a Devops transition among the Web department (~30 persons)
- Developed collaboration in a distributed team
- Evangelized best software development practices and open-source contributions

- Interacted with local open-source communities to organize coding events
- Drafted many Request For Proposals responses, in Drupal and web-related
- Collaborated with HR department to scale up the team
- Proudly ranked 13th at the Applied Security Event NorthSec in 2017 (on 40 teams)

**Drupal Practice leader** at Savoir-faire Linux, Montreal **January 2013- October 2016** http://savoirfairelinux.com

drupal | php | python | training | project management | architecture | ci/cd

- Collaborated with the team in Paris on a Request for Proposals for Paris-Dauphine university. Contract won: http://my.dauphine.fr.
- Acted successfully as project manager and architect in numerous projects
- Built a skillful team of Drupal experts (up to 5 backend developers)
- Designed Drupal development and deployment processes used among the team for clients projects
- Initiated a fair development program to help non-profit organization with their IT needs
- Architected and developed the new portal of Polytechnique school (http://polymtl.ca)
- Acted as Ring (formerly SFLphone) Scrum Master

Free software consultant at Savoir-faire Linux, Montreal October 2007- December 2012

http://savoirfairelinux.com

c++ | c | jenkins | voip | training | php

- Worked on the open-source R&D project Ring (formerly SFLphone)
- Worked as embedded Linux developer in an international leader in high performance digital imaging (TeleDyne Dalsa)
- Developed the high-traffic Portable North Pole platform
- Trained professionals to use LAMP stack
- Certified as Professional Scrum Master (Pyxis)
- Audited internal processes as member of the auditors team (ISO 9001)

#### **EDUCATION**

Internship at Society of Arts and Technology, Montreal
2006 - 2006

# Department of Computer Science and Operations Research (Student Exchange) at University of Montreal

2005 - 2006

mathematics | image processing | computer graphics

Computer Engineering Degree at Polytech Nice-Sophia, Sophia-Antipolis 2002 - 2005

algorithm | java | mathematics

#### **CONFERENCES, PUBLIC SPEAKING**

Free software for Meals-On-Wheels communities @ Debconf 2017 5 August 2017

django | python | github | travis

**Docker and Microsoft Azure** @ Docker Meetup Québec

1 March 2017

docker | docker swarm | azure

Various hacknights and code sprints organizer for the Sous-Chef project @ Montreal Python

25 August 2016

django | python | github | travis

CI/CD in a Drupal multisite environment @ Drupal Camp 2015 15 October 2015

drupal | ci/cd | jenkins | git | aegir

Gain productivity with Drush @ Drupal Camp 2013

**15 October 2013** 

drupal | drush

**LANGUAGES** 

French

**English** 

Native

Fluent